I want to show you how to research anything because research is power.
أريد أن أريك كيف تبحث في أي شيء لأن البحث هو القوة.
It's also a skill and once you learn how to do it, you can literally teach yourself
إنها أيضاً مهارة وبمجرد أن تتعلم كيف تفعل ذلك، يمكنك حرفياً تعليم نفسك
whatever you want.
ما تشاء
And if come to realize lately that most people don't know how to research, they know how
وإذا أدركت مؤخراً أن معظم الناس لا يعرفون كيفية البحث،
to search.
للبحث
And there's actually a very big difference because when you search, you're relying on other
وهناك في الواقع فرق كبير جدا لأنه عندما تبحث، أنت تعتمد على الآخرين
people to think for you and we don't want that.
الناس يفكرون من أجلك ونحن لا نريد ذلك.
We want to do better.
نريد أن نفعل أفضل.
So yeah, research has levels to it.
لذا نعم، البحوث لديها مستويات لذلك.
My system that I use has four, so I'm going to walk you through them.
النظام الذي أستخدمه لديه أربعة، لذا سأقوم بتجريبهما لك.
One is your surface search.
الأول هو بحثك السطحي
This is where you need to start, but this is also where most people stop.
هذا هو المكان الذي تحتاج إلى البدء فيه، ولكن هذا هو المكان الذي يتوقف فيه معظم الناس.
This is your Google search, the TikTok videos, the YouTube explanations, the AI answers.
هذا هو بحثك في جوجل، فيديوهات تيك توك، شرحات يوتيوب، إجابات الذكاء الاصطناعي
And the problem with stopping here is that you're getting compressed conclusions and you're
والمشكلة في التوقف هنا هي أنك تحصل على استنتاجات ضغط
not understanding how they were built.
لا يفهمون كيف تم بناؤها
So let's take an example.
لذلك دعونا نأخذ مثال.
Let's say that you search up what is dark matter and you get results like, well, it
لنفترض أنك تبحث عن المادة المظلمة وتحصل على نتائج مثل
makes up 85% of the universe.
يشكل 85% من الكون.
We can't see it.
نحن لا نستطيع رؤيته
It affects gravity.
إنه يؤثر على الجاذبية
You get all these facts, but you still don't understand things like how do we know that
أنت تحصل على كل هذه الحقائق، ولكنك لا تزال لا تفهم أشياء مثل كيف نعرف أن
it exists or what evidence actually supports it or what competing theories to it are?
أو ما هي الأدلة التي تدعمها بالفعل أو ما هي النظريات المتنافسة لها؟
So how do you level one correctly?
إذاً كيف تحدد مستوى واحد بشكل صحيح؟
You use it as orientation for yourself and not education.
تستخدمها كالتوجيه لنفسك وليس التعليم
So your goal at this level should be learning the vocabulary, identifying the key concepts
لذا يجب أن يكون هدفك في هذا المستوى هو تعلم المفردات، تحديد المفاهيم الرئيسية
and generating more questions for yourself, figuring out what you still don't know and
وتوليد المزيد من الأسئلة لنفسك، وتكتشف ما لا تزال لا تعرفه
what you're still really curious about.
ما زلتِ فضوليّة حقاً
You spend 10 to 15 minutes doing the search at level one, like maximum.
أنت تقضي 10 إلى 15 دقيقة في البحث في المستوى الأول، كحد أقصى.
And then you stop and you ask yourself, what do I still not understand?
وبعدها تتوقف وتسأل نفسك ماذا لا أَفْهمُ بعد؟
And that question is your doorway to your level two.
وذلك السؤال هو بابك إلى المستوى الثاني
Level two is source expansion.
المستوى الثاني هو توسيع المصدر
This is where you begin to really investigate.
هذا هو المكان الذي تبدأ فيه في التحقيق حقا.
So what does this look like?
كيف يبدو هذا؟
This is clicking sources and articles.
هذا النقر على المصادر والمقالات.
It's reading entire studies instead of just the summary of the study.
إنه يقرأ دراسات كاملة بدلاً من مجرد ملخص للدراسة.
It's following links and citations and references.
إنه يتبع الروابط والإقتباسات والإشارات
This is where you go from.
هذا هو المكان الذي تذهب من.
What is this?
ما هذا؟
To where did this come from?
من أين جاء هذا؟
Let's go back to the dark matter example.
دعونا نعود إلى مثال المادة المظلمة.
Now you're no longer staying on Google or TikTok.
الآن أنت لم تعد تبقى على جوجل أو تيك توك
You are opening the NASA page.
أنتِ تفتحين صفحة "ناسا"
You're clicking the cited research.
أنت تنقر على البحث المذكور
You're opening up the Galaxy Rotation Curve Study and you're seeing the observations by
أنت تفتح دراسة منحنى دوران المجرات وترى الملاحظات من
scientists.
العلماء
So this is so important because now you are seeing the evidence and not just the conclusion.
لذا هذا مهم جداً لأنك الآن ترى الأدلة وليس الاستنتاج فقط.
So how do you level to properly open everything?
إذاً، كيف تُسطح لفتح كل شيء بشكل صحيح؟
Don't just read the page and close it down.
لا تقرأ الصفحة وتغلقها
You should have five to ten tabs open of everything that you're looking at.
يجب أن يكون لديك خمسة إلى عشرة علامات مفتوحة من كل ما تنظر إليه.
You should be following citations backwards at this point.
يجب أن تتبع القوائم إلى الوراء في هذه المرحلة.
So going from the article to the study to the original data, all of that is always pretty
لذلك الذهاب من المقال إلى الدراسة إلى البيانات الأصلية، كل ذلك دائما جميلة
much linked.
مرتبطة جداً
You should be prioritizing.edu's.gov's, published papers, any content from the expert in the
يجب أن تكون أولوية.edu's.gov، والمقالات المنشورة، أي محتوى من الخبراء في
field.
الحقل
And you should be asking yourself, what is this claim that I'm looking up based on?
ويجب أن تسأل نفسك، ما هو هذا الادعاء الذي أبحث عنه على أساس؟
Because if you can't answer that, you are probably still back at level one.
لأنّك إذا لم تستطع الإجابة على ذلك، فأنت على الأرجح ما زلت في المستوى الأول.
I get into level three, which is pattern recognition.
أدخل المستوى الثالث، وهو التعرف على الأنماط.
And I think that this is the level where the truth really starts to show up because
وأعتقد أن هذه هي المرحلة التي تبدأ فيها الحقيقة في الظهور
at this level, your main focus is comparing multiple sources and you're paying attention
في هذا المستوى، تركيزك الرئيسي هو مقارنة مصادر متعددة
to agreements and contradictions among them.
التوصل إلى اتفاقات وتناقضات بينهما
You are identifying repeated ideas that you see.
أنت تحدد الأفكار المتكررة التي ترونها.
You're really looking for things that show up repeatedly across those sources, whether
أنت حقاً تبحث عن الأشياء التي تظهر مراراً وتكراراً عبر تلك المصادر، سواء
they are numbers or questions or ideas or arguments because it shows that they are important.
إنها أرقام أو أسئلة أو أفكار أو حجج لأنه يظهر أنها مهمة.
Let's say that you read six different sources on dark matter.
لنفترض أنك تقرأ ست مصادر مختلفة حول المادة المظلمة.
And six of them said that Galaxy rotation does not match visible mass and one of them
وقال ستة منهم ان دوران المجرة لا يتطابق مع الكتلة المرئية
said that maybe gravity laws are wrong.
قال ربما قوانين الجاذبية خاطئة
So now you really see the consensus happening within the topic itself.
لذا الآن ترى حقاً أن الإجماع يحدث داخل الموضوع نفسه.
You see the outliers and you see the debate that exists and you're starting to get a real
يمكنك أن ترى الاختلافات وترى النقاش الموجود و تبدأ في الحصول على حقيقية
understanding of what you're learning about.
فهم ما تتعلم عنه.
At any level, three properly, you look for overlap.
في أي مستوى، ثلاثة بشكل صحيح، تبحث عن التداخل.
So what do most of the sources agree on?
إذن ما الذي يتفق عليه معظم المصادر؟
You also should be noticing the disagreement.
أنت أيضاً يجب أن تلاحظ الخلاف
So figure out where the experts diverge on that topic.
لذا اكتشف أين يختلف الخبراء حول هذا الموضوع.
You should be ranking the evidence that you find.
يجب أن تصنف الأدلة التي تجدها
You can separate it into strong evidence versus speculation.
يمكنك فصلها إلى دليل قوي مقابل تكهنات.
You can also create like three mental buckets or write them down if you want to obviously.
ويمكنك أيضاً إنشاء مثل ثلاث سطل عقلية أو كتابتها إذا أردت ذلك.
But one is information you find that's consistent across all the sources.
ولكن واحد هو المعلومات التي تجدها التي تتوافق بين جميع المصادر.
Another one for information that is debated and another one for information that is uncertain.
آخر للمعلومات التي يتم مناقشتها والآخر لمعلومات غير مؤكدة.
And by doing that, you are actually teaching yourself and building your own intellectual
ومن خلال القيام بذلك، كنت في الواقع تعليم نفسك وبناء فكري الخاص بك
judgment on the topic.
الحكم على الموضوع.
A level for the depth and framework level because this is where you stop learning information
مستوى للعمق ومستوى الإطار لأنه هنا حيث تتوقف عن تعلم المعلومات
and you start thinking in systems.
و تبدأ في التفكير في الأنظمة
You are asking better questions.
أنت تسأل أسئلة أفضل.
You are building mental models of the topic that you're researching and you're starting
أنت تبني نماذج عقلية للموضوع الذي تبحث فيه و تبدأ
to connect ideas across different fields of research.
لربط الأفكار عبر مجالات مختلفة من البحث.
So you're really looking for the structure behind the topic of whatever you're researching.
إذاً أنت تبحث حقاً عن الهيكل وراء موضوع ما تبحث عنه.
Instead of asking what is dark matter, we're asking deeper questions.
بدلاً من أن نسأل ما هو المادة المظلمة، نحن نسأل أسئلة أعمق.
We're asking things like why does gravity behave this way or what assumptions are built
نحن نسأل أشياء مثل لماذا الجاذبية تتصرف بهذه الطريقة أو ما هي الافتراضات التي بنيت
into our existing model of dark matter or what would have to be true for all of this
في نموذجنا الحالي للمادة المظلمة أو ما يجب أن يكون صحيحاً لكل هذا
to be wrong.
أن أكون مخطئاً
You are really training yourself to think more deeply and to ask better questions, which
أنت حقا تدرب نفسك للتفكير بشكل أعمق وتطرح أسئلة أفضل
is very important in research.
هو مهم جدا في البحث.
The level we are asking second order questions, we are not just asking what, but why and
مستوى نحن نسأل أسئلة النظام الثاني، نحن لا نسأل فقط ماذا، ولكن لماذا و
what if we are building on our mental models.
ماذا لو كنا نبني على نماذجنا العقلية؟
So take a piece of paper and draw it out in front of you, right?
لذا خذ قطعة من الورق ورسمها أمامك، صحيح؟
Dark matter, it's a placeholder for missing math.
المادة المظلمة، انها مكان لافتقار الرياضيات.
It's inferred from gravitational effects.
لقد تم استنتاجها من تأثيرات الجاذبية
It's not directly observable.
لا يمكن ملاحظتها مباشرة.
Draw it out so you can see the map of it and start connecting it out.
رسمها حتى تتمكن من رؤية خريطة لها وبدء ربطها.
Dark matter is physics.
المادة المظلمة هي الفيزياء
It's cosmology.
إنها عالمية.
It's philosophy of science.
إنها فلسفة العلوم
You can take the information you have and draw it out into what is evidence, what is uncertain,
يمكنك أن تأخذ المعلومات التي لديك وتسحبها إلى ما هو دليل، ما هو غير مؤكد،
what about the topic is the limitations of our knowledge.
ما حول الموضوع هو حدود معرفتنا.
When you start to draw it out in front of you and build a model that you start to see
عندما تبدأ في رسمها أمامك وبناء نموذج تبدأ في رؤيته
all of the connections and you start to see all the missing gaps.
كل الاتصالات تبدأ في رؤية كل الفجوات المفقودة.
And it is crazy how much that really helps your understanding of it.
ومن المجنون كم هذا يساعد الفهم الخاص بك حقا.
The thing about research is that it is not linear, it is a loop.
الشيء حول البحث هو أنه ليس خطيا، إنه حلقة.
So you search and then you expand and then you compare and then you build those mental
لذا تبحث ثم تتوسع ثم تقارن ثم تبني تلك العواطف العقلية
models.
النماذج
And from those mental models you get better questions.
ومن تلك النماذج العقلية تحصل على أسئلة أفضل.
And then you repeat it all over again with the better questions you search and you expand
وبعد ذلك تكرر كل شيء مرة أخرى مع الأسئلة الأفضل تبحث وتوسع
again and you compare and you build more models.
مرة أخرى وتقارن وتبني المزيد من النماذج.
And that is how you learn how to think for yourself.
وهكذا تتعلم كيف تفكر بنفسك
That is how you truly begin to understand something.
هكذا تبدأ حقاً في فهم شيء
And that is how following your curiosity becomes very, very powerful.
وهكذا تتبع فضولك تصبح قوية جداً جداً